hi
everyone welcome to my little talk today
on health insurance 101
i hope you learned something um so this
talk is meant to be a basic overview of
how health insurance works
we're going to go over some of the ins
and outs of various things you will
encounter and what you'll want to know
when you're purchasing
and using a health insurance plan
if you ever have any questions after
this if you
something doesn't make sense or you have
a particular question about your plan
i am always here to answer your
questions and i'm happy to
chat with you if you want to text me or
send me an email or you can comment on
this youtube video i guess
and i will try to help you out as best i
can
so let's get started here
what are we going to talk about today
how does health insurance work
what do all of these fancy insurance
words mean
what kind of health insurance plans are
out there and which one should you get
how do you get a health insurance plan
how do you know what your plan covers
what kind of limitations should you
watch out for so that you don't get
[__] by your health insurance company
and most importantly how much is this
all gonna cost me
anyway couple caveats before we begin
unfortunately health insurance is way
more complicated than this little talk
i'm giving
if i were going to get into every
nitty-gritty detail of health insurance
that i know about we would be here for
an entire day and we would all be very
confused and sad at the end of it
there are many kinds of health care
services out there we've got primary
care you've got surgery you've got
orthopedics cancer treatments mental
health services
dermatology neurology physical therapy
etc etc forever and ever
for the purposes of this talk today i'm
usually going to
say doctor or doctor's office but that's
just to be consistent and general
all of this information is going to
apply to all of these other medical
services
as well the numbers and the figures that
i use today are for educational purposes
only
i don't necessarily know what a
particular doctor's visit is going to
cost you i also don't necessarily know
what any particular health insurance
plan's premium is going to line up with
a certain deductible or out of pocket
etc um i don't know everything either i
have been working for a physical therapy
clinic for about a year and a half now
i deal with health insurances every day
but i still
quest ask questions all the time and
also so does my manager
and most importantly here the american
healthcare system
sucks and none of us should have to
worry about any of this
and with all that out of the way let's
get started
so let's start out big picture here how
does health insurance work
so when you have a health insurance plan
every month you will pay a bill to your
insurance company that's called a
premium
the premium is set it does not change
month to month
whether or not you use any medical
services
your health insurance company then pools
every member's premiums
into a big pot when you see a doctor
some of that money from that big pool of
everyone's money
goes towards paying your doctor instead
of you having to pay the full bill
you will almost always still have to pay
some of that bill but it's going to be
much less than you would have to pay
if you didn't have insurance here's
an example of how this works i'm just
going to use really low numbers just to
show you what i'm talking about
let's say that with your plan you are
covered at 90
for a certain doctor's visit you go to
see the doctor
and the bill is a hundred dollars now
because you're covered at ninety percent
your insurance is going to pay ninety
dollars of that bill
um and you will only pay that remaining
ten dollars
with your health insurance plan you also
paid a 40 premium this month
but the total you paid will still come
out to less than you would have paid
with no insurance and now like all
insurances this is a gamble because
maybe you didn't go to the doctor that
month so you just paid your premium
and you didn't receive any services for
it but maybe you broke your leg and
you're going to need
lots of services and lots of doctor's
visits and
all of those visits would have cost you
10 000
but with your health insurance you're
only going to pay a thousand dollars
because you're insured
now before we go any farther with this
let's take a look at an example of a
health insurance plan
to go over some terms now this is a very
bare bones description of a plan we're
just going to go over the most
important features right now so for this
example this
is alice's health insurance plan alice
has a
350 dollar premium her deductible
is 1500 she has a co-insurance
of 60 percent and her yearly out of
pocket
is 7 000 so let's break down what each
of these terms mean
and how they apply to a health care plan
so first that premium that's something
we talked a bit about already this is
the set amount of money that alice pays
every month
in order to keep her plan active this
money gets paid directly to the health
insurance company
up next is the deductible the deductible
shows the amount of money that alice has
to pay towards medical services
before her insurance is going to cover
any of her
bills now the existence of the
deductible can be kind of surprising to
people who don't know about it and i
just want to acknowledge that it
feels very unfair to pay monthly for a
plan that isn't actually going to cover
you
until you've already paid a lot of money
towards your health care services
and now this money that goes into the
deductible that's money that gets paid
to a doctor's
office and your insurance company keeps
track
of what gets paid to who and then they
start to tally that up
add it up in the deductible um until you
reach that fifteen hundred dollars
um up next we have that coinsurance
alice has a 60 coinsurance which means
that once her deductible is met
she will only pay for 60 of her visit
charges
another way people often describe the
coinsurance would be to say that
alice is covered at 40 which is a way to
say what percentage the insurance covers
instead of what alice is responsible for
if you're ever talking with an insurance
representative
or a doctor and they quote you a percent
and you're not sure whether they're
saying
this is the percent the health insurance
covers or they're saying this is the
percent that you are responsible for
just ask them to clarify and that last
one here
is going to be the yearly out of pocket
now this
is the total amount that alice would
have to pay
for medical expenses in the year once
alice
pays that seven thousand dollars towards
medical bills
the rest of her payments for the year
are 100 covered
most of the time the deductible is
included in the yearly out of pocket
which means that alice just has to pay
seven thousand dollars flat
it wouldn't have to be that eighty five
hundred dollars to meet that out of
pocket
however the premiums that you pay those
are not included
in your deductible nor are they included
in your yearly out of pocket
another item i want to go over that you
will see in a health insurance plan a
lot is something called a co-pay
for some plans either once you meet your
deductible or instead of paying into a
deductible for certain services
you pay what is called a co-pay this is
a set amount of money that you have that
you pay
at every appointment that you have we'll
talk a little bit more about how co-pays
work later
another set of terms you will often hear
when discussing your plan or when you're
looking for a doctor
is in and out of network health
insurance companies have
contracts with certain medical groups
certain pharmaceutical companies and
also particular private practices
and these contracts basically say yes we
as a health insurance guarantee that we
will pay for patient services at this
particular doctor's office
and the doctors agree yes we as a
doctor's office will let the health
insurance company pay a certain
percentage of our patients
bills depending on how their plans work
so doctors that have these contracts
with insurance companies are considered
in network with the insurance company
and doctors that don't have a contract
are called out of network basically
you always want to be in network with a
doctor that you're seeing
if you see a doctor who is not in your
health insurance's network
you either won't be covered at all by
your health insurance or you're going to
be covered at a much
lower rate than you would if you were
seeing an in-network doctor
most doctor's offices will list on their
websites
what insurances are in their network and
so you can check online and if you're
ever not sure you can always call a
doctor's office and ask them if they
take your insurance
insurance companies will also list what
doctors are in network on their websites
um you can also always call your
insurance company to ask
a lot of times insurance company
websites will also have a place where
you can put in your zip code
and then they'll be able to pull up the
doctors that are near you
who are in your network
so let's talk about what kind of health
insurance plans are out there
health insurance plans tend to fall into
two big categories
you've got your low premium high
deductible plans
and your high premium low deductible
plans
generally speaking plans with a high
premium have a low deductible
and vice versa there are also plans that
are in the middle that are like
medium premium medium deductible plans
but for the purpose of today i'm mostly
going to talk about the two ends of the
spectrum to sort of
demonstrate the differences between the
two and figure out which one seems more
appropriate for you
so there's no right plan out there it's
just what's best for you based on your
health needs
to look at some examples of how these
plans might be different and might serve
different people
let's look first back at alice's plan
from before
now alice has a relatively low premium
as hard as that might be to believe
the average premium in america this past
year was around 450
a month now in exchange for alice's low
premium however
she has a very long way to go with her
medical bills before she gets any
coverage from her plan
and she has an even longer way to go
before she could possibly be covered
at a hundred percent by reaching her out
of pocket
let's look at a different plan now this
is betty's plan
betty pays a higher monthly premium than
alice does but betty's coverage is going
to kick in at a much
lower deductible betty is also going to
have
a lower coinsurance when she is covered
past her deductible and she's also going
to have a much lower yearly out of
pocket which means that in the event
that she pays
all of that money she's going to be
covered a lot sooner than alice might be
um i want to also add right now that
um generally your yearly preventative
visits so your physical
your flu shot any other shots you might
need or
any kind of tests you need yearly based
on your age or gender like a colonoscopy
or a pelvic exam
those kind of preventative visits are
almost always already covered at a
hundred percent so don't let a plan that
has a high deductible scare you away
from going to those um
yearly preventative visits you'll still
be covered for those
copay carol is back let's check back in
with carol for a second here and her
plan
um first of all if your plan includes
co-pays
you might have copays only for certain
services this is not a guarantee that
it's going to apply to
all of your the different types of
doctors you might see
these also might differ in amount
between which services you get
often a visit to your regular doctor is
going to be cheaper than a visit to a
specialist
and your health insurance company will
determine what kind of doctor
is a specialist a plan that has co-pays
is usually a mid-high premium
kind of plan co-pays for a doctor's
visit usually range from about twenty
dollars to seventy dollars per
appointment
in my experience there are also co-pays
for things like an emergency room visit
or an x-ray
and those can cost a lot more those can
sometimes be three or four digit numbers
depending on your plan your copays will
contribute to your yearly out of pocket
they usually don't contribute to your
deductible though
now we know a little bit about what kind
of plants are out there and you're
probably asking yourself
what kind of plan should i get again
there is no
right plan out there there's no magic
plan that's perfect for everyone it's
just what is best for you
based on your health insurance or based
on your health needs
people who are looking at probably
wanting a low premium
high deductible plan are people who are
generally in good health
someone who doesn't go to the doctor
that often
and someone who feels secure with a
riskier gamble with your coverage
if you have a high deductible plan and
you have a medical emergency
you're going to have a pretty big chunk
of money that you owe basically all at
once
instead of less money that you owe all
at once plus higher premiums that you
pay throughout the year
with a high premium load deductible plan
that's going to make more sense for
people who do expect to have more
frequent doctor's visits
people who might take multiple daily
medications
and also people who want to feel more
secure
in the event that they do have a medical
emergency
this doesn't only apply to people who
have particular medical conditions maybe
you
play a high impact sport and that's
going to increase your chances of injury
or maybe you have a family history of
some type of illness or condition that
you want to be
prepared to cover expenses for also this
is where my service provider caveat
comes in
when you're thinking about how much you
see doctors throughout the year
you need to think also about things like
mental health care or chiropractors or
how much prescription medication you
take because those will all
be under your health insurance and
health insurance is going to determine
how much
those are going to cost for you
throughout the year
real quick here um quick aside i would
like to
explain how your health insurance
actually processes a charge
if your coverage for a particular visit
goes through your deductible and you're
out of pocket
um the way this works is after you have
an appointment
the doctor is going to record the
charges
for the services that they provided and
they're going to send those charges to
your health insurance company
first the insurance company is going to
apply your plan's coverage to these
charges
and then they're going to send the
adjusted bill
back to your doctor's office at this
point the doctor's office is going to
send
you a bill for the remaining charges for
what you're responsible for
now this process can take several weeks
which is why you usually won't know how
much a visit costs
until after you've had it now if you
have a copay this process is much more
simple
when you go to your doctor's appointment
the doctor's office will tell you that
you have a copay
they will have you pay that copay before
you leave the appointment
and then they will send the rest of the
charges to the health insurance company
and then you will not receive a bill
later
so next question where do i get health
insurance from
so there's three main routes to getting
health insurance
the first one and the one that most
people go through
is through their employer most
workplaces offer benefits to
full-time or salaried employees
at the end of each year your workplace
will share the particular plans that
they offer
and then you get to pick which one you
think is best for you
now the main perk of getting health care
from your work is that it is
usually at least partially subsidized so
you're paying less for your premiums
than you would
if you had not if you had enrolled in
the plan independently
your monthly premium is also usually
automatically deducted from your
paycheck
so you don't have to worry about paying
a bill on time because your work just
does it for you
your work might also offer you vision
and dental which we don't really have
time to talk about here but
most of the time eye care and dental
care are
not included or they're very expensive
under a
regular health insurance plan so if you
get extra vision and extra dental
insurance it's going to generally be
cheaper in the long run for you to get
that eye
and dental care your work might also
offer you something that is called an
hsa card
hsa stands for health spending account
and it's basically an account that your
work provides to you
that you can put money into to spend
only on health care
this is a nice way for you to be able to
put aside money at the beginning of the
year
or like after a particular bonus in the
event of a health emergency
and usually your work will match up to a
certain amount that you put in so you
kind of get like double money on that
for free
um so if you do wind up with one of
those make sure you do put some money
into it
um the hsa card is um usually something
that applies to a low premium plan
since the company is expecting you to be
spending more money out of pocket
before your coverage kicks in
the second way to get health insurance
is to enroll in a plan directly through
a health insurance company
why would you want to do this maybe you
work part-time or you are self-employed
so you don't get benefits from work
if your works plans don't cover you very
well
or if there is a particular plan that a
particular health insurance company has
that you know is going to be the right
plan for you and maybe it's not offered
by your work but you've said
that's okay i know that i need this plan
in order to feel secure about my
health care bills through the year now
the third option for getting health
insurance is to be eligible for a
government subsidized health insurance
plan now i could do an entire separate
powerpoint on medicare and medicaid
but i'm going to give you one slide
about it so the us government
does subsidize health care for certain
populations in this country
those populations generally fall under
the categories of
old people and poor people medicare
is the program for old people anyone who
is 65 years of age or older is eligible
for medicare
medicare also covers people of any age
with als
or esrd which stands for end-stage renal
disease
medicare is also available on a
case-by-case basis
for people with other disabilities to be
eligible you need to be collecting
social security disability insurance
for two years and you also have to meet
some other criteria
that medicare will provide for you
now medicaid is the government program
that provides
subsidized health care for people with
very low incomes
now beyond this income requirement you
must also
be one of these things you must either
be pregnant
caring for a child blind or almost blind
disabled in some other way caring for a
disabled person
in your home or 65 years or older
the veterans association also has health
insurance available for veterans and
their families
now i want to be clear here that these
government subsidized plans are not free
they still have premiums and you still
usually have to pay co-pays or pay into
a deductible
um these plans are i'm sorry not a
deductible pay into an out of pocket
um these plans just cost less than
private health insurance does
there's also a lot of hoops that you
have to jump through in order to get one
of these plans
except for when you're 65 and then you
just get medicare automatically
okay now we know what health insurance
is
we know what it does we know where to
get it
and we know what kinds of plans are
available to us
so now let's say you've got a plan
you're looking to get some medical
services
how do you know what services your plan
covers how do you know how much it
covers
you need to call your insurance company
and speak to someone who can look up the
information in your plan
i cannot stress enough how important it
is
for you to do this if you are going to
access
a new type of service if you're going to
see a new doctor
or if you're going to see a doctor who
works for a different company or a
different medical group
even if you're pretty sure you know what
your coverage is
i highly highly encourage you to call
your health insurance company first
verify your benefits how do you do this
on the back of your health insurance
card and also on their website they're
going to have a customer service number
to call
and this line is basically dedicated to
helping people
understand their plans when you call
you will usually first go through an
automated screening where a robot is
going to ask for your information a lot
of these lines have robots that say that
they can help you with particular
questions about your plan
but i say you should always speak to a
human
who can look up your information once
the
robot tells you that they're
transferring you to a representative
you are going to be on hold for a while
i have been on hold for up to an hour on
dedicated lines for health
care providers verifying patients
benefits
these call centers are just really busy
sometimes
be patient stay on the line someone will
answer your call
once you do get to speak with a human
they will have you provide
all of your insurance information your
name and date of birth that sort of
thing
and then they will ask you what kind of
service you are looking to access
the rep will also ask you whether you
are in and out of
in or out of network you should know the
answer to this already before you call
unless you are calling specifically to
ask whether you are in or out of network
with a certain provider again you always
want to be
in network the representative will then
be able to tell you whether you have a
copay or
coinsurance for the appointment they'll
be able to tell you how much you've met
towards your deductible if you're not
sure if you've met it yet
they can also tell you what kind of
limitations you might
have for a particular visit or a
particular medication
we'll talk a little bit more about
limitations in a couple of slides
now these representatives they do this
all day so a lot of times they
talk really fast or they might use words
that you're not familiar with something
that maybe we didn't go over here or
maybe you forgot
um if anything the representative says
doesn't make sense to you
or you miss something that they say ask
them to repeat themselves
ask them to clarify they are there for
you
they are there to help you understand
your plan and it is a huge pain to have
to call again
if you missed something or if you didn't
understand something that someone told
you
now when you're finished with your call
this is very important
you need to ask for the representative's
name
and you need to ask for something called
a call reference
and call reference is an id number
that's attached to the call
all the calls that go in and out of the
in these um
insurance centers these call lines
they're recorded
and each of these calls is paired with
an id number that's the call reference
in the event that the representative
gives you the wrong
information you can use this call
reference number to file a claim
if you ever think you're overcharged or
if you ever think that what the
representative quoted you was incorrect
or is not properly reflected in a bill
that you get
last before you receive services you
should compare the information that you
got from the health insurance
representative
with the information that your doctor's
office got when they verified your
benefits
let's say a health insurance
representative tells you you have a 20
copay for this appointment but then when
you get there
the doctor's office tells you you have a
50 copay
this is a huge discrepancy and
especially if you're going to need
multiple visits for this doctor you're
gonna either be
extremely overcharged or you're going to
owe a lot of money that you didn't think
that you owed
so if this ever happens you need to have
the doctor's office
call the insurance company again to
verify and it also doesn't hurt for you
to call them again to verify
as well when you call
there are some general things that you
should not do when you are on the line
fastest ways to look like a noob the
first one of these
is calling the doctor that you want to
see instead of calling the health
insurance company
to ask about your coverage you can call
a doctor's office to ask whether you're
in network
with the office but they're not going to
be able to tell you any specifics about
your coverage
without getting your insurance
information and verifying your benefits
themselves
you can always ask a doctor's office to
verify your benefits and have them
call you back and go over the
information that they got with you
but they might not get to it for a few
days and technically this is something
you can do
on your own so it just takes a little
bit more time
to get that done if you're asking your
doctor's office to do it
the next way to get yourself into
trouble is
to expect anyone to know exactly how
much you will be charged for a visit
i cannot tell you how many people call
me and say
you know i have blue cross insurance how
much am i going to be charged for a
visit
i don't know this is the fastest way to
tell me that you have no idea how your
health insurance plan works
even if you're calling your health
insurance company if you ask
how much will a visit cost you're not
going to get very far
unless you just have a co-pay and they
can say yep forty 40
for a visit there neither a doctor's
office
nor health insurance rep is going to be
able to say your visit will cost you x
dollars
they'll only be able to tell you what
your coinsurance is
or what you what percent of the bill
they're going to cover
a particular doctor's office might be
able to give you a
ballpark estimate for how much a bill
would be
but then you still have to know how much
your insurance is going to cover for it
this kind of ballpark quote is also not
a guarantee
of how much an appointment is going to
cost and you won't be able to hold
anybody liable
if that bill comes out to be much more
than you were expecting there's
really not a lot to be done about this
except to assume that the charges will
be higher
than what you are quoted another thing
that people will often ask when they
call is they'll say
am i covered for a certain service
now this wording is kind of tricky and
vague
do you mean am i in network do you mean
will my health insurance cover some
portion of this bill
do you mean will my health insurance
cover 100
of the bill when a doctor's office when
a doctor's office
or a health insurance company says you
will be covered for your visit
what that usually means is that you are
in network
with the doctor that you're trying to
see and that some of your bill will be
covered
i have patients who get confused and
people who've gotten upset in the past
because our office has told them
you're covered for physical therapy in
your plan meaning
your health insurance company will pay
for some of the charges
but this patient thought that you are
covered meant
that they were covered at 100 percent
and that they would not have a bill
so then when they got a bill later they
were confused and they were frustrated
and they owed money that they didn't
realize that they were going to need to
owe
so in order to avoid that when you're
asking about coverage you need to ask
by how much you are covered what
percentage
am i covered at another big
new move here is to ignore discrepancies
between what you think your coverage is
and what the doctor's office
says your coverage is i have experienced
on multiple occasions patients who
refuse to pay their co-pays because they
don't think they have any
um i've had a patient who thought that
their deductible was a thousand dollars
less
than what it actually was um and all
these patients wind up with bills
that they didn't think that they had to
pay um
but they do and there is absolutely no
way to challenge those charges you just
owe that money
another big mistake i see patients make
is having the mindset of
i know my insurance will cover me for
this because i really need this
treatment
if it's not covered in your plan you're
not covered
end of story this of course snowballs
into the biggest new move of all
which is assuming that your health
insurance company has your best
interests at heart
your health insurance company is a
for-profit corporation
that makes its money by not paying for
member services and by keeping the
premiums that the members pay
in order to grow the business's wealth
they will look for any reason to deny
you coverage they will make you jump
through lots of hoops to prove that your
treatment is medically necessary
the biggest lie any of these companies
will tell you is that they are here for
you
that they care about your health and
that they will do everything that they
can
to save you money on your bills
truthfully they want to make this
process
as difficult and complicated as possible
as it
is for you so that you either don't
access those services in the first place
so they don't have to pay for them or
that they make you pay more than you
expected to and you won't challenge it
because
it's not worth it to dispute the claims
so let's take a look at what some of
these limitations are
so that you don't get [__] by your
health insurance
first and most importantly is to make
sure that you are in network with the
doctor that you see
this is your first step when you're
looking for care when you're looking for
a new doctor
if you get a recommendation or there's
someone you want to see and they're
not in your network forget about them
look for a doctor who's in your network
next thing to know here is whether or
not you've met your deductible
we get patients who come in knowing that
they're covered at 80 percent for their
visits
and then they don't understand why
they're getting charged so much
it's because they haven't met their
deductible yet so that 80 coverage has
not
started yet um excuse me something to
remember here is that your deductible
resets
every year for most plans it resets
at the beginning of the calendar year so
january 1st
some plans it resets sometime in the
middle of the year though so make sure
you know
when in the year your deductible resets
another thing to watch out for is visit
maximums
for a doctor that you might see
regularly for a time like
chiropractor or dermatologist or
physical therapist
your insurance might only cover a
certain number of visits per year
this is really important to know before
you start treatment
so that you can budget those visits
accordingly and you can also make a plan
with your doctor
for how to use those visits most most
effectively
there are also maximums that exist for
medication refills
and that is something you should also
discuss with your doctor if they're
trying to prescribe you something that
you can only get a certain amount of
for the year
um this i'm sorry let me go back this
these visit maximums this is one of the
places where doctors
love to deny you coverage if you exceed
the maximums even if you still need more
treatment even if you still need more
medication
your health insurance will not pay for
it if you have exceeded those maximums
and they love to deny those claims there
are ways to appeal
sometimes if you have a certain type of
maximum or if your maximum is really low
there is a way a lot of times for your
doctor to appeal
to your health insurance company for
more visits that process can take a long
time though
so if you are expecting to need to do
that you should talk with your doctor
really early ahead of time and say hey i
know i'm going to need more than
15 physical therapy visits for the year
what can we do to get you more visits um
and have that conversation really early
so that you're not reaching the end of
your um
maximums and realizing you need more and
then there's just not enough time
for them to put in for more without you
needing to wait like two months
to get more visits um something else to
look at is
whether or not your insurance company
considers the type of doctor you are
seeing a specialist
for example physical therapy is
considered a specialist by some of the
insurances
that my company takes and it is
considered a regular office visit
for some of the other types of
insurances
that we take this is important to know
because usually a copay
or a co-insurance is going to be a
different amount
depending on whether you are going for
an office visit
or seeing a specialist so just make sure
you know
when you see a certain type of doctor
what your insurance company categorizes
that particular type of doctor as
water break
okay something else to look out for
when you are seeing a doctor who is not
your primary care
is whether you need a prescription or a
referral
sometimes you might need a prescription
to see a doctor who is not your primary
care
you sometimes also might need a referral
that has
the specific doctor that your primary
care wants you to see
the specific location that they want you
to be seen at
and the specific number of visits that
they want you to have
with this other doctor your insurance
company
will need this particular prescription
that's called a referral
with the specific number of requested
visits and you can't have
more of those visits until your primary
care writes you
another referral for you to get more
visits
this is not the case with every type of
insurance
but there are some that do require it so
make sure when you call to verify your
benefits you know
whether or not you need a prescription
to see a different doctor
or whether you can access them directly
without going to your primary care for a
prescription first
this is also important to know when it
comes to
medications um there are
certain prescription requirements for
things like how often you can refill
a dose or how many particular you know
pills you can get at a certain time
some insurance companies have certain
automatic regulations
for this and they can only change them
if the requirement
is um if your doctor writes in the
prescription dose like
this patient needs this refilled every
seven days
that sort of thing um or it's it's
possible for
the pharmacy to say your insurance
company will only let us refill this
every 10 days
your doctor needs to write a a specific
note to say
to refill it more often um that's sort
of the
sort of thing you want to know before
because if you run out of it
it's very possible that your doctor will
not be able to get
that updated prescription in the same
day and then you will be out of
medication
um the last one on here is
pre-authorization
which is something that your doctor's
office usually takes care of
and you don't even know that it's
happening um basically even if
a certain specialist or a certain
medication is covered by your plan
sometimes that specialist or your doctor
is going to need to submit
extra material to your health insurance
to demonstrate that
this treatment is medically necessary
the insurance company will read your
doctor's notes and grant a certain
number of
specialist visits or a certain amount of
medication
that they deem appropriate for your case
a lot of times too the doctors will have
to resubmit these materials
to demonstrate that the treatment is
working and that you need more
specialist visits
or you need more medication in order to
be completely better
if your insurance requires that you are
pre-authorized for something
sometimes your doctor's office will have
you fill out a particular form that goes
to your insurance company excuse me
in this instance you need to work with
your doctor and let them coach you
on how to fill out that form to
demonstrate that your condition is
serious enough to need treatment
but that it is also has really good
potential for you to improve or be cured
by the treatment
doctors don't like health insurance
companies either and it because it makes
their job a lot harder it makes it
harder for them to get
their patients the care that they need
so always work with your doctor and work
with your doctor's office
on um what to put on any of these forms
in order to get you the most visits or
get you the right amount of medication
for your particular condition and always
hear
if you don't know the answer if you
don't know whether you have a limitation
on a visit or a medication
call your health insurance company and
ask always get a call reference
always get the representative's name
now of course it is time to figure out
how much
is all of this going to cost you per
year
health insurance in this country is
stupid expensive
and as such so is health insurance i
will give you
a couple of examples of possible ways
you might use your health care through
the year
and what kind of fees you're going to
pay in each of these scenarios
i highly encourage you also to browse
around on different health insurance
websites
look at the kind of plans that they
offer apply some of these examples
to the plans in order to give you an
estimate on the amount that you might be
looking at paying
in a year so let's move on to this first
scenario here so
scenario number one is what i would call
your dream scenario this is the absolute
lowest that you could pay for healthcare
in a year in this scenario you have a
low premium
high deductible plan during the year the
only time you visit the doctor are for
your yearly preventative visits
excuse me you get your yearly flu shot
and whatever other vaccines you are due
for
all these visits are covered at 100 you
are not prescribed any medications nor
do you already take
any daily prescriptions and you do not
attend any additional doctor's visits
throughout the year in this case the
only money that you would be paying for
health insurance
is your monthly premium and this is one
of those times where you kind of lose
out on your health insurance gamble
because
you're paying your monthly premium and
you're receiving very few services
through the year
however this is still the lowest that
you could pay for healthcare in a year
while still
having a health insurance plan
scenario 2 is the opposite end of this
spectrum
you still have a low premium high
deductible plan but this year you tear
your acl
playing basketball right after the tear
you go to the er
because you're in a lot of pain at the
er they do an x-ray
they tell you you've likely torn your
acl they schedule you to follow up for
an mri just to be sure
after the mri confirms the tear you are
scheduled with a surgeon
who repairs your acl after the surgery
your surgeon prescribes you pain
medications
and of course a physical therapy and
during the next eight months you see
your physical therapist
two to three times a week and you return
to your surgeon for several follow-ups
to make sure that you are healing
properly
your surgeon also refers you out to an
orthopedic specialist to continue to
monitor your progress
after your surgery has healed now in
this scenario
on top of your expected premium that you
pay each month
you have paid an er copay which is
usually a three-digit sum
a copay for your x-ray and for your mri
a charge for your surgery by which time
you have probably met your deductible
and your coinsurance is going to kick in
next you will be paying the copay for
your prescription pain medication every
time you refill it
you'll pay the co-insurance for every
follow-up with your surgeon
you will pay the coinsurance at each
appointment you have with your physical
therapist
and you will pay a co-insurance for
every orthopedic appointment that you
have
generally speaking with this scenario
during the year you have paid your
premium each month and you have reached
your yearly out of pocket
this is the absolute maximum that you
would pay for health insurance
in or for health care in a year there's
a lot of middle ground
in between these two extremes so let me
give you some things to consider
to help you work out a reasonable
estimate for you
as to what you might pay in a year
do you take a prescribed medication you
will pay for every refill
so factor in how many times you get this
medication refilled in a year
do you see a mental health therapist how
often are those visits
are you the kind of person who just
seems to get sick a lot in this case
how often do you tend to see a doctor
when you do get sick
do you play a high impact sport or
participate in an activity where
injuries are common
if so you know like you should know that
you could wind up
like scenario two and end up paying your
whole out of pocket
for care if you get injured do you have
a family history of something that you
want to be screened for
or do you have a medical condition that
requires particular tests
if so you might want to see what tests a
plan covers
and by how much same goes if you know
that you're going to need to see certain
doctors throughout the year besides your
regular doctor for your annual physical
keeping these sorts of things in mind
when you're looking at a plan and
budgeting for the year
for your health care payments can be
really helpful when estimating
about how much you might be paying this
kind of thing can also really help you
decide whether you're going to be
looking at a low premium high deductible
plan
high premium low deductible plan or
something that's sort of in the middle
all right so this is going to bring us
to the end of the slide show today
these are the final things that i do
want you to walk away with today
health care and health insurance in this
country are stupid expensive
and it sucks health insurance companies
prey on people
who don't understand their plans they
love to deny you coverage if they can
get away with it
and they will not think twice about
leaving you to fend for yourself
if you get into a financial bind that
being said
your doctors know this too and they want
to work with you to get you care
so always work with your doctors and
your doctor's office
to make sure that they help you get the
most out of your coverage
along with that it is very important to
always call your health insurance
company before verify your benefits
yourself
before you receive a new type of service
or before you see a new doctor
every time you call get the
representative's name
get a call reference every single time
even if you're just calling to double
check something
last thing here this was gaining more
traction during the democratic primary
but has kind of fallen by the wayside in
terms of social justice movements that
people are like really aggressive about
right now
we need government subsidized health
care in this country for
every person who lives here if any of
your representatives are not
in support of medicare for all i really
highly suggest you call
write email etc express your opinions to
those representatives and if your
representatives do support it
please let them know that you are in
support donate for their reelections
there is also bernie sanders's medicare
for all platform
that you can also donate to i know that
both
health and finances are still very taboo
conversation topics
in most circles but people are really
suffering
under this burden and the more that we
talk about it the more that we can
realize that this is a problem for
everyone
and hopefully that will elevate it as an
important issue that needs to be solved
that is the end thank you for coming to
listen to this
i hope that you learned something i hope
this was not too overwhelming
i know that this is a lot of information
just for a 101 discussion
um if you have any questions i'm
available all the time please text me
call me email me um dm me on groupme i
don't know
comment on this youtube video um
i am happy to answer your questions even
if it's something super specific about
your particular plan
and if i don't know the answer i will
try to talk to someone who does
that is all thanks so much for listening
bye